**Phone:** 55 (84) 98722-8804 **E-mail:** jalerson@gmail.com

**GitHub:** http://www.github.com/jalerson **Website:** http://jalerson.me

LinkedIn: http://www.linkedin.com/in/jalerson

## Jalerson Lima, MSc

## Senior Ruby on Rails Developer and Professor

Energetic and accomplished Senior Developer with a track record of success in managing complex IT modernization and system integration projects. Multilingual management professional providing critical oversight to teams and projects with strengths in consulting, program and project management, business process optimization and process improvements. Solutions driver who bridges the gap between business and technology while envisioning the bigger picture.

## Work Experience

2012 - Present

**Senior Ruby on Rails Developer and Project Leader** - Laboratory of Technology Innovations in Healthcare – Natal, Brazil

Lead web developer of the Telepediatrics project. Telepediatrics is a web-based system, developed in Ruby on Rails, to support non-specialist doctors in pediatric appointments, allowing them to discuss cases with remote medical specialists. In these days, Telepediatrics is really big and complex project, which handles sensitive and law-protected data, supporting doctors by using complex algorithms to perform statistical analysis and calculations, such as insulin therapy, Z-Score and percentiles of anthropometry measures, as well as automatic detecting issues on neurodevelopment, vaccination and so on. Currently, I'm also coordinating the team that is developing the Telepediatrics mobile application in Android, iOS and Windows Phone, as well as building an API to integrate our system to our mobile app.

I also had the opportunity to start, from scratch, the Dengue National Observatory, which is a web-based system, built in Ruby on Rails, to support public healthcare agents to track cases and proliferation spots of the Aedes Aegypt mosquito. System in action: <a href="http://youtu.be/kWvhaHXv-70">http://youtu.be/kWvhaHXv-70</a>.

During two months, I also coordinated the SISCOAPES project, which is a web-based system built in Django, to support the federal government in monitoring the operation of medical residents in healthcare centers. All the system features were remotely negotiated with public healthcare specialists from the Brazilian Ministry of Health.

2014 - Present

Fulltime Remote Professor of Software Engineering and Programming Skills – Federal Institute of Education – Natal, Brazil

In 2014 I accepted the challenge to teach remotely at the Distance Education Campus of the Federal Institute of Education. During these two years I developed online courses using Moodle about algorithms, programming skills and web development. Last year, I wrote an educational book called Structured and Object-Oriented Programming with Ruby which has been used by my students. Currently, I'm producing a series of educational videos about programming web-based applications using Ruby on Rails.

2010 - 2014

Fulltime Classroom Professor of Software Engineering and Programming Skills – Federal Institute of Education – Natal, Brazil

Fulltime professor of software engineering, software programming and computer basics at the Federal Institute of Education at Rio Grande do Norte (IFRN). In these past six years as professor, I had the opportunity to teach

**Phone:** 55 (84) 98722-8804 **GitHub:** http://www.github.com/jalerson E-mail: jalerson@gmail.com Website: http://jalerson.me

**LinkedIn:** http://www.linkedin.com/in/jalerson

thousands of students, conduct research and educational projects, supervise students in their projects and so on.

I have experience on teaching programming introduction and algorithms using structured-Portuguese languages, Java, Ruby and Python. As professor and developer, I am always trying to figure out better ways to teach programming skills to my students, using, for example, educational tools with this purpose, such as Robocode, Scratch, Codecademy, etc.

However, I also have experience on more complex subjects, teaching my students on how to build their own software and web-based applications using modern software languages, such as Java, PHP, Ruby and Python, using modern MVC frameworks like Ruby on Rails, Codelgniter, CakePHP, and using modern databases like MySQL and PostgreSQL.

2009 - 2010 Senior Ruby on Rails Developer - Sync Systems - Natal, Brazil

> Senior Ruby on Rails developer of the internal management system of the Telepesquisa Company, built in Ruby on Rails. Project built by me from scratch: negotiating and collecting functional requirements at client's site. The Telepesquisa management system had to import millions of records of other partner companies. I also was the main developer of the Bluesync, which is a Bluetooth marketing software developed in Java.

Remote Systems Analyst Consultant - Symetrix Corp. - Colorado Springs,

Remote Systems Analyst Consultant of the Eye of the Eagle project, which was a system to prevent tax evasion of the Rio de Janeiro government. I worked in Java, C and C# components, handling with smart cards and RFID (Radio-frequency Identification). In this position, I had my first experience negotiating features and deadlines with the clients in English.

**Developer and Software Architect** - Real Security – Natal, Brazil

I worked as a software developer and architect to develop an Electronic Security Monitoring System used by the company. The system, built in Java, had to manage all the security signals sent by devices located in the client's houses.

Web Developer - Ministry of Education - Brasília, Brazil

I worked as web developer to build the Knowledge Connections Portal to the Secretary of Continuing Education, Literacy, Diversity and Inclusion of the Ministry of Education. The portal, developed in Mentawai (Brazilian MVC Java Framework), it was nationally used to register and monitor projects conducted by federal universities.

Web Developer - Brazilian Agency for the Aquaculture Development - Natal,

Web developer of the RECARCINE Portal, which was a web-based system, built in PHP, to manage projects of the Brazilian Agency for the Aquaculture Development.

2008 - 2009

2007

2007

2006

Phone: 55 (84) 98722-8804 **GitHub:** http://www.github.com/jalerson Website: http://jalerson.me LinkedIn: http://www.linkedin.com/in/jalerson E-mail: jalerson@gmail.com

## Education

2012 - 2014	Master of Science in Systems and Computing - Federal University of Rio Grande do Norte – Natal, Brazil
2008 - 2010	<b>Specialist in Systems Engineering</b> - Open Superior School of Brazil – Vila Velha, Brazil
2004 - 2007	<b>Bachelor of Science in Software Development</b> - Federal Institute of Education – Natal, Brazil